時は戦国、乱世の時代。
からくり人の住むジパング国では群雄割拠して合戦に明け暮れ、
からくり武芸者たちも勝利と栄光を目指してしのぎを削っていた。
そしていま、からくり武芸者ナンバー１を目指す、とてつもないヒーローが誕生した！
ムサシ、見参でござるだス！
からくり剣豪伝ムサシロード
男はいつでも　世界の真ん中で
いちばん　強くなる日を
AH! AH! 夢見て
心の刃　大空にふりかざし
冒険の旅の　幕を開ける
ジパング国を　さすらう剣豪
その名　からくりびと　ムサシ
GO! FIGHT!
鍔迫り合いの音が
眩しい人生
戦い　昨日よりも　今日　強い
BUGEI! 二刀流　ムサシ
明日は　輝くぞ
鍔迫り合いの音が
眩しい人生
戦い　思い切りと　静けさと
BUGEI! 二刀流　ムサシ
みけんが　きらめいた　ムサシ！！
반역자라는 오명을 썼던 무사시는 한조의 손으로 처형될 처지에 놓였다.
Under the disgrace of being called a traitor, Musashi was about to be executed by Hanzō.
그러나 그 때, 주베가 검호들을 이끌고 구하러 와 주었다.
But at the right moment, Jūbee and others came to save him.
무사시는 뜨거운 우정에 울고 말았다.
Musashi cried, thanks to the burning friendship.
그러나 지팡구 제일의 길은 멀다.
But the road to becoming the number one of Jipangu has no end.
사내 무사시의 숙명의 길은 어느 방향인가?
Which road of fate should Musashi take?
무사시, 꿈의 백번승부
Hundred Matches
in Musashi's Dreams
정월 기분에서 벗어나지 못한 에도토피아의 거리에 눈이 내렸다.
In the spirit of new year's holidays, snow was covering the streets of Edotopia.
그 쯤 무사시는 내일부터의 여행을 앞두고 에도 성에서 센히메, 코지로하고 카드놀이를 하고 있었다.
Meanwhile, Musashi was playing cards with Senhime and Kojirō in Edo castle, having a day to go for a journey.
다고 해안에 나가 멀리 바라보니 (하얗게 솟은)
(*후지산 봉우리에 눈이 내리고 있네)
"Watching far away from the coast (of Tago)..."
(*...it is snowing on the tall and white Fuji peaks.)
(백인일수 4장)
(4th poem of Ogura Hyakunin Isshu; lit. 100 poets and poems at Ogura)
-이럇!
-Mine!
그대 그리워 잠 못 이루는 밤은 (유독 길구나)
(*방문의 틈새조차 야속하게 느껴지네)
"A night lost in thought longing for you (knows no end)."
(*Even the tiny doorframe gap grows cold.)
(백인일수 85장)
(85th poem)
-이럇!
-Mine!
따스한 햇살 (품은 화창한 봄날)
(*들뜬 마음 그대로 꽃은 지고 마는가)
"Warm sunlight (fills a fine spring day)."
(*Calm mind is not there; flowers die)
(백인일수 33장)
(33rd poem)
-이럇!
-Mine!
변치 않기를 바라는 이 세상 (해변의)
(*어부 배저어 가는 모습 무상함이 느껴지네)
"The shore desiring for (no changes)..."
(*binds the fisherman rowing a boat, with or without a rope)
(백인일수 93장)
(93rd poem)
-이럇!
-Mine!
서리 내리고 귀뚜라미 우는 밤 (차디찬)
(*멍석 위 옷자락 베게삼고 홀로 누워 있는가)
On a frosty night with crickets (crying),
(*with clothes as my pillow I am lying)
(백인일수 91장)
(91st poem)
-이럇!
-Mine!
어스름한 (밤 새벽달이 밝구나 창밖을 보니)
(*마을을 뒤덮은 새하얀 눈꽃송이)
The moon (outside the window is bright)
(*Snow covers the village tonight)
(백인일수 31장)
(31st poem)
-이럇!
-Mine!
더 이상 재미없소! 난 그만두오!
It's not fun anymore-dasu! I quit-dasu!
오, 난 이렇게나 얻었구나.
And I got this much.
무사시. 그런 반사 신경으로는 제일의 무예가가 될 수 없지.
Musashi. You won't cut it as a top-class martial artist, with that kind of reaction.
이런 얘들 장난은 코지로한테 딱 어울리오!
Such child's play suits Kojirō perfectly-dasu!
뭐라?!
What?!
자, 자, 무사시! 설날이니까 그렇게 화내지 마.
Calm down, Musashi! It's the first day of the year; chill out.
정말, 왜 너희 둘은 그렇게 사이가 나쁜 거야?
Goodness. Why can't you two get along?
코지로 따위, 처음 만났을 때부터 정말 싫었소!
I hated Kojirō ever since I met him for the first time-dasu!
오츠루하고 갈라져 수행길을 떠난 그 날.
Back in the day that I bid farewell to Otsuru and went on a journey of training...
著、ちょっと待ちでござるだス！
待てというのは私のことか
상대가 되어 주길 부탁드리오.
I'd like you to be my opponent-dasu.
お弁当付けて何をいう。
얘야, 식사 후에는 낮잠 자는 게 좋다.
Kiddo, you'd better take a nap after a lunch.
꼬마 따위 아니오!
I'm not a kiddo-dasu!
悪いことはいわん。村へ帰って畑の手伝いでもするんだな。
己、馬鹿にするでないでござるだス！
飛び上がるなんて卑怯でござるだス！
後ろから切りつけるというのは卑怯ではないのか？
잡소리 말고 바로 승부를 내오! 자, 오시오!
Stop complaining so that we can settle this right here right now-dasu! Come-dasu!
よかろう。武芸の道がいかに厳しいものか教えてやろう！
ムサシ、見参！
必見！燕返し！
さらばだ、坊や。バカめ。
こら！勝負はまだついっ。。。
そんな馬鹿な。。。
생각하면 또 속이 뒤집어지오!
Thinking about it makes me furious-dasu!
그래도 무사시, 그 때에 비해서 꽤나 강해지지 않았니?
But Musashi, you did become stronger compared to that time before!
당연하오!
That's obvious-dasu!
나, 보쿠덴 스승님에게 목숨을 걸고 수련받았소!
I was trained under my master Bokuden, with my life at stake-dasu!
꽤나 쓰라렸지만...
It was pretty bitter-dasu...
甘い、甘い！
師匠！
なにするだス！
馬鹿もん！実際の戦いで助けてくれる奴があると思うか！
おいしいよ男だった。。。死ぬまで剣を離さぬとは。
つきあり！
보쿠덴 스승님, 요즘 어떻게 지내시려나...
I wonder how fares Master Bokuden nowadays-dasu.
무사시?
Musashi?
예, 무엇이오?
Yes, what is it-dasu?
아까 오츠루하고 갈라져 수행길을 떠났다고 했잖아?
You told me that you went to train yourself after bidding farewell to Otsuru, right?
오츠루는 누구야?
Who is Otsuru?
설마 무사시의 애인인가?
Could she be Musashi's lover?
어라, 무사시도 가볍게는 못 보겠는걸?
Hey, Musashi isn't to be underestimated, I guess!
그러면 곤란하오!
You embarrass me-dasu!
그 날, 타쿠안 스님에게 혼나서
That day, I was scolded by the monk Takuan,
나무에 매달려진 날 오츠루가 구해주었소!
but Otsuru saved me, hanging down from a tree-dasu!
もう大丈夫ね。
でも、オツルちゃんが和尚に叱られるだス。
あたしのことは心配しないで。 あたしはムサシさんがスズメと遊んでるの見て、とても嬉しかったわ！
だって、ムサシさんは本当はとっても心が優しいんだって分かったんだもの！
いや、そんな、照れるだスよ！
ムサシさん？
あ、なに？
これ、御結びよ。
オツルちゃん！
和尚さんだってきっとわかってくださるわ。
うん。
ムサシが逃げたぞ！
-자, 무사시 씨, 빨리!
-알겠소.
-Hurry up, Mr. Musashi!
-Right!
きっと、ゆめをかなえてね。
ありがとう、おいら、きっと、ジパングナンバーワンの武芸者になってみせるだス！
お、オツルちゃん、あ、あの、
え？なに？
あの、た、達者で言ってほしいだス。
元気でね！ムサシさん！
나, 그 날 정했소. 지팡구 제일의 무예가가 된다면 오츠루를 부인으로 맞이하겠다고!
I decided that day-dasu. I'll invite Otsuru to become my wife when I become the number one martial artist of Jipangu!
오츠루...
Otsuru...
그래서 무사시.
So, Musashi...
오츠루, 네가 지팡구 제일이 될 때까지 쭉 독신이 되는 거야?
Will Otsuru remain as a bachelorette until you become the best of Jipangu?
그, 그렇게 되는 것이겠소.
I... I guess so-dasu.
오츠루도 불쌍하네. 그렇게는 할머니가 되어버리겠어.
Too bad for Otsuru. She'll become a granny!
그건 곤란하오!
That won't happen-dasu!
그렇소. 나, 이런 곳에서 놀고 있을 틈 따위 없소!
I see-dasu. I do not have time to be playing like this-dasu!
시끄러운 놈.
What a noisy brat.
그래도 오츠루는 행복하겠네.
But you know, it sounds like Otsuru would be happy.
그래요.
Right.
조금 전만 해도 내리던 눈은 평년보다 따뜻한 겨울 때문에 어느새 그쳤다.
Thanks to the winter warmer than the usual, the snow has stopped before they knew it.
미야모토 마을의 무사시이오!
I'm Musashi from Miyamoto village-dasu!
주베 님을 뵙고 싶소!
I want to see Jūbee-dasu!
환영합니다, 무사시 님.
Welcome, Musashi.
그래도 이런 시간에 어쩐 일이십니까?
What made you find me this late?
나, 주베 씨를 이기고 싶소. 상대해 주시기를 부탁드리오!
I want to defeat you, Jūbee-dasu. I ask you to be my opponent-dasu!
이것 역시 무사시 님답군요.
This also is like you, Musashi.
일단 앉아서 이야기를 해 보죠.
Please, sit down, and let's talk.
무사시 님. 무예가라는 것은 무예만을 닦는 자일까요?
Musashi. Do martial artists work on their martial art skills and skills only?
그러니까, 무예가라고 하니까, 역시 무예를 닦는 것이 제일이오.
We call them martial artist after all-dasu, Working on skills stands as the top priority-dasu.
싸움이라는 것에는 전술, 전략이라는 것이 필요.
You will need tactics and strategies in battles.
곧, 병법서를 공부하는 것이 제일의 무예가의 길.
In other words, you should study strategies from books to become a top martial artist.
나, 책을 잘 읽지 못하오.
I am bad at reading books-dasu.
만화는 좋소만.
I like comics, thought-dasu.
뭐든 책을 읽는 것만이 공부인 것은 아닙니다.
Thankfully, reading books isn't the only way to study.
그 외에, 공부할 방법이 있소?
Are there other ways to study-dasu?
나, 가능한 한 간단한 게 좋소.
I'd like the simplest one-dasu.
쫌만 하면 팍 되는 놈으로.
The one that will just work!
그런 건 없습니다.
That isn't possible.
역시이오...
Thought so-dasu...
일단은 라이벌에게서 배우는 것입니다.
To begin, you can learn from your rivals.
라이벌이오?
From rivals-dasu?
무사시 님이 지금까지 만난 무예가를 생각해 보신다면 알 수 있습니다.
You will understand once you think about the martial artists you've met so far.
내가 만난 무예가...
The martial artists I met...
수행길을 떠난 나는 미야코 궁전에서 벤케이를 만났소.
During my journey of training, I faced Benkei at Miyako Palace.
出たな、ベンケイ！ムサシがお相手をするでござるだス！
いざ、真情に勝負するだス！
やめろやめろ！ 今夜は記念すべき千人目のよる。
その相手は歯ごたえのある大物に決めておる。
さあ、子供はとっとと失せ！
黙れ！おいら、子供じゃないだス！ 剣聖ボクデンの免許皆伝の一番弟子でござるだス！
うるさい小前が！
買ったばかりの刀が。。。
もはやここまで。ゲームオーバーよ。
こうなったら煮るなり焼くなり好きにするだス！
仕事の邪魔だ！とっとと失せ！
그 때, 그 우시와카가 나타났소.
That moment, that Ushiwaka appeared-dasu.
待て。
なにか？
その腰のものを置いて行っていただくおば。
おお、これを？
そなたの太刀。 まさに我が千本みに相応しいもの。
おとなしく置いて行ってはくれぬか。
ならぬな。
그렇다면... 얻어서 내 것으로 만들 때까지!
If then... I'll simply take it myself!
이놈!
You bastard!
京を荒らす不届きもの。麻呂が退治してくれようぞ！
なんだと？！
バカそうな！
どうしたのかな。
くそ、小癪な！
何？！
どうだ。麻呂にはかなうまい。
なんの、これしき。
ま、まいた！この通りでござる！
無用の長物 もっと修行を積むのだな。
お待ちください！どうかお名前を！
麻呂はウシワカ。ウシワカともう。
ウシワカどの。ああ！お待ちを！
なにとぞ！なにとぞベンケイを！
나, 그 때, 위에는 위가 있다는 것을 깨달았소.
That moment, I learned that there is always someone better than me-dasu.
하늘은 공평하다고 하지만...
They say that the god does not give two gifts-dasu, but...
우시와카 씨는 미남에, 게다가 강하기까지 하니 앙큼하오!
Not only Ushiwaka is handsome, but he's also strong, and that's unfair-dasu!
무사시 님도 꽤 하는 남자랍니다.
Musashi, you're a pretty good man too.
정말이오?
Really-dasu?!
역시!
I knew it!
수줍어하고 있을 때냐, 무사시! 질풍노도의 후반을 기다려라!
This is no time to be shy, Musashi! Wait for the stormy latter half!
무사시와 주베의 무예담은 밤이 깊어져도 계속될 뿐이었다.
There was no end to Musashi and Jūbee's conversation on martial arts deep into night.
그리고 저와 같이 있을 때 만난 자가 호조인 님.
And we met Hōzōin when we were journeying together.
그 사람도 강했소!
That person was strong too-dasu!
다음은 호조인 님과 승부를 보고 싶소!
I want to have a match against Hōzōin-dasu!
刀をワシに向けるとはいい度胸。よかろう。
ただし真剣勝負以外は受けぬが、よいかな？
望むところだス！
変わった槍でござるだスな！
この鎌槍こそ我が宝蔵院流の必殺武器。
いいぞ！勝負！
鎌の部分を計算に入れなかったんだス！
見たか。これぞ宝蔵院流鎌槍の特技。突くだけでなく切るきのおもその間万能槍。
覚悟！
このままでは漬け込む透きがないでござるだス！
とどめだ！
逃げるか、小僧！
違うだス！狭い道場は息が詰まるから外へ出ただけだス！
負け惜しみだけは一丁前だな！
動けないだス！
それ、くし刺しだ！
覚悟！
誰だ！
貴様。。。
おぬしは！
相手はまだ少年。たってとあらば拙者がお相手いたす。
葵の紋章。諸国を見回る警察の長官のジュウベエどのか！
勝負を忘れたか、ホウゾウイン！覚悟！
参った。
どうしてでござるだス？今の勝負は相打ちでは。。。
いやいや、自慢の槍をkikiochiされてのは拙者の負けでござる。
igou shoujin tukamaserimasuru.
ほ、本当？
やった！やったでござるだス！
그 때의 무사시 님도 강했지요.
Musashi, you were strong too back then.
그래도 주베 씨 덕이오!
But it's all thanks to you-dasu, Jūbee!
그리고 쿠사리가마를 쓰는 바이켄 님.
And Baiken, the yielder of Kusarigama.
그런 무기, 나 그 때 처음 봤소!
I never saw a weapon like that before then-dasu!
しまった！
いったた、何するんだス！
や、やめるばい！
やめろというのが分からんのか！ネットワーク
おらの負けばい！
이 승부 후 우리 사이 좋아졌소.
After that match, we became friends-dasu.
라이벌을 넘은 우정이란 것이겠소.
Friendship born of rivalry.
이 소리는?
What is this sound?
내 배가 울렸소. 배고파져서...
My stomach just rang-dasu. I'm hungry...
알겠습니다. 식사를 준비해 드리지요.
Alright. I'll get you a meal.
맛있소!
It's so good-dasu!
그런데 무사시 님. 그 콩을 젓가락 하나로 집을 수 있을까요?
By the way, Musashi. Can you pick one of those beans with one chopstick?
어? 하나로?
Huh? Using only one?
젓가락 하나로는 무리이오.
It's impossible with only one chopstick-dasu!
그럼 둘이라면 어떻습니까.
Then, how is it using two?
이거라면 쉽소.
This is easy-dasu.
그런 것입니다.
That's how it is.
그런 것?
That's how it is?
코지로 님에게 츠바메가에시라는 비검이 있다고 해도, 그 칼은 하나.
Kojirō may have a secret sword named Tsubamegaeshi, but only one sword is used.
칼은 둘이 있다!
You have two swords!
이도류...
Dual blade...
언젠가 우연히 보여주신 이도류의 기술.
You have showed me the technique of using dual blades before.
그걸 공부한다면...
If you explore further...
이도류...
Dual blade...
무예 대회에서의 무사시와 주베의 번외 시합.
From the extra match between Musashi and Jūbee in the martial arts competition...
初め！
いかん。このままではやられるだス。 こんなめでは。。。
何とか切り抜ける技はないだスか？
그 때, 우연히 보여준 것이 이도류였다.
What he showed us back then is the technique of dual blades.
그 자세를 공부한다면 천하무적의 무예가가 될 지도 모릅니다.
If you build upon that posture, you might become the matchless martial artist as well.
이도류를 공부하는 것이겠소!
So I should study dual blades-dasu!
코지로 님과 함께 여행하면서 자신의 검술을 수련하며 이도류를 완성하는 건 어떨지요.
I suggest you to develop your technique of dual blades to perfection on the journey with Kojirō.
알겠소. 나, 꼭 이도류를 공부해서 숙명의 라이벌, 코지로를 쓰러뜨리겠소!
Understood-dasu. I will take Kojirō down by studying the technique of dual blade-dasu!
이도류를 완성한 새벽녘에는 이 괴물을 퇴치하십시오.
Once you develop the technique of dual blade, you will eliminate these monsters.
야마타노오로치?
Yamata no Orochi?
츠치구모?
Tsuchigumo?
신이 다스리던 시대부터 명도 천공환, 천지환을 지키고 있다고 전해지는 괴물입니다.
They are monsters that are told to be protecting the sacred swords named Tenkūmaru and Tenchimaru.
(Tenkūmaru: Sword of the sky, Tenchimaru: Sword of the world)
그 괴물을 퇴치하면 그 명도가 손에 들어오는 것이오!
So by getting rid of those monsters, I will claim those excellent swords-dasu!
그 때야말로 무사시 님은 천하제일의 검호가 되겠죠.
When that time comes, Musashi, you'll become the best of the best swordsmen around the world.
주베 씨, 감사하오!
Thank you so much-dasu, Jūbee!
나, 힘껏 해 보겠소!
I'll do that with all my might!
이것이 바로 무사시의 이천일류 개안의 힌트가 되긴 했지만
This is the hint to Musashi's realization of Niten'ichiryū,
(Niten'ichiryū: 二天一流; other name for Nitouryū=二刀流=dual blades)
배가 불룩해져서 바로 잊어먹을 결정을 한 무사시.
but Musashi will probably forget soon as his tummy is full.
과연 숙명의 여신은 미소를 지어 줄까?
Will the goddess of fate smile at him?
カラのポケットに　ツキが
飛び込むことも　あるさ
おっきな声で　笑えば
あしたには　朝が来る
無くすものなんか　何もないさ
やっちゃえ！イケイケ！
手ぶらは　強いぜ
てなもんだ　のーてんきに行こう
人生　てなもんさ　チャンスが　ほら
しっぽを振って　追ってくるぜ
てなもんだ　のーてんきに行こう
未来も　てなもんさ　あしたが　ほら
両手ひろげて　笑ってるぜ
센히메 방위와 이도류 수행길에 떠난 우리 셋은 일단 동쪽으로 향했소.
To guard Senhime and develop the technique of dual blade, we headed to the east first-dasu.
섬뜩한 늪에 다가갔을 때,
When we were at an eerie swamp,
말도 안 되게 거대한 두꺼비를 조종하는 이상한 카라쿠리 무예가가 나타났소.
a strange Karakuri martial artist yielding a giant toad has appeared-dasu.
그 자의 정체는 이하 사천왕의 하나, 지라이얀!
The name of that guy is Jiraiyan, one of the Four Rulers of Iga!
다음 이야기! 거대 두꺼비 요술 지라이얀이오!
Next story! Giant Toad Magic, Jiraiyan-dasu!
질풍노도의 여행이오!
It'll be a stormy journey-dasu!
다음 이야기
거대 두꺼비 요술 지라이얀
기대하세요!
Next Episode
Giant Toad Magic
Jiraiyan
Look forwards for it!